This is a work of fiction.
Any resemblance to real persons, groups or events is purely coincidental.
Yes, that's right!
そうなんですよ
家の椎茸　クラシックを聞かせていたら
When I put on a classical music record, our shiitake mushrooms
すっかり大きく成長したんです
started growing at an amazing speed!
へえ　そうなんだ
Really?
人工の雷で電気を流すともっと成長するらしいよ
I heard that electricity from artificial lightning makes them grow even more.
Electricity?
電気
Yeah. The mushrooms feel threatened by the strong electric current,
うん　強い電流の刺激を受けて
危機感を抱いたきのこの菌糸が
so their filaments start growing rapidly to leave descendants behind.
子孫を残すために　活発に生育するらしい
Just shut up and do your homework.
いいから　お前は宿題やってろ
A helicopter, huh?
ヘリか
あっ　そう言えば
That reminds me of Ogi. He liked helicopters.
小木がヘリ好きだったな
@ 湮·Molly／小然·酸菜／喵儿·小冷／时末·竭力而为
KamiGami
Today is a real mess, but I get over it with a sigh
複雑に構えた今日が 息を呑んで澄ましてる
身に覚えあるだろう 君はどうしたい
You get the idea, right?
What do you wanna do?
何もなかったそぶりで  かばう痛みはもう
You act as if nothing happened
As if your heart didn't ache
心強いくらいに 急かすんだ
It almost feels encouraging,
the way you're rushing me
掴んでこぼして 不完全な僕たちが
Hold it and let it overflow
We're all imperfect
光って見えない 未来の自分を創れるなら
I can't see it well in the light,
but if we can change our future selves
目覚めるまま走れ 蜃気楼を追い越して
Wake up and run
Go and surpass the mirage
変わりたいまま走れ 自由な違和感で
Try to change and run
with the discomfort of freedom
届きそうな輝きと今を選んでいこう
We can reach that shining light
Follow it into the present
飛びたつ手を知らない
Don't hesitate to act
深い 浅い 呼吸を重ねて
Deep or quick, just keep breathing
Hyouka
Ogi? You mean Ogi Takahiro from class 2-B?
小木さん
Does the Sun Shine on the Peaks?
群山是否天晴
二年B組の小木高広さんですか
Who's that supposed to be?
誰だよ
I told you, he's in class 2-B.
ですから　二年B組の
I'm talking about an Ogi you don't know.
お前の知らない小木だよ
He was our English teacher in junior high.
中学の英語教師だ
You know, right, Satoshi?
里志　あいつだよ
Of course I know Mr. Ogi. But I didn't know he liked helicopters.
もちろん小木先生は知っているよ
だけど　ヘリが好きだなんて知らなかったな
I thought everyone knew he loved them.
有名だと思ったがな　小木のヘリ好きは
Did you know, Ibara?
伊原は知っているだろ
Nope.
さあ
That's weird.
おかしい
How come I know but they don't?
俺が知っていて　あいつらが知らないとはどういうことだ
We've been together since Kaburaya Junior High,
二人とも鏑屋中から一緒で
and Ibara and I have been in the same class all along as well.
しかも伊原は　ずっと同じクラスだった
There's no way she wouldn't know.
知らないはずはない
So what about this Mr. Ogi?
その　小木さんという方がどうかしたんですか
Well... Ibara, don't you remember?
まあ　ちょっとなあ
伊原　覚えてないか
That time when a helicopter flew over Kaburaya Junior High.
いつだったか鏑屋中の上をヘリが飛んだことがあっただろ
A few dozen times as I recall, but yeah.
何十回　かね
One of those times, Ogi rushed to the window in the middle of class to look at the sky.
そのうちの一回
授業中に小木が突然　窓に駆け寄って空を見上げたことがあった
He kept watching until the helicopter disappeared into the distance.
ヘリが遠ざかっていくまでずっと見ていて
He just smiled and said something like, "Oh, I love helicopters,"
ヘリが好きなんだとか何とか笑ってごまかしながら
by way of explanation when he resumed class.
授業に戻ったことがあったろ
うん　そこまで言われると思いだしちゃうな
Yeah, now that you've described it in detail, I remember there being something like that.
あったわ　そういうこと
Was that Ogi?
あれって小木だっけ
It was.
小木だったよ
I'm glad my memory wasn't just playing tricks on me.
よかった　覚え違いじゃなかった
That's weird.
それはおかしいな
おかしいって言われても　そういうことがあったんだよ
It might be weird, but it happened all the same.
But what about when that squadron of JSDF helicopters flew by?
でも　自衛隊のヘリがスコードロンくんで飛んできた時は
That was quite a sight,
かなりの見ものだったのに
but I don't recall Ogi reacting like that.
小木先生がそれに反応したという記憶がないんだよね
What's a squadron?
スコードロンって何だ
A group of aircraft.
編隊
How did you know it was the JSDF?
どうして自衛隊だと分かった
Can you think of any other helicopters that would fly in formation?
ほかに編隊飛行をしてるヘリコプター集団に心当たりがないから
And you're sure Ogi was there at the time?
その場に小木がいたのは間違いないのか
Pretty much.
と思うけど
I remember I looked up the word AGM in my English dictionary when I saw the helicopters.
確かそのヘリを見て　英語の辞書で「AGM」って言う単語を引いた覚えがあるから
AGM?
AGM
What's that?
それなんですか
It's short for "air-to-ground missile".
空対地ミサイルの略語だ
But yeah, if something like that had happened,
確かにな
そんなのが来たら　小木ならグランドに出て踊り出しそうだ
surely Ogi would be out on the grounds dancing with joy.
Well, I doubt he'd actually be dancing.
踊りはしないだろうけどね
It was a figure of speech.
物の例えだ
うん　ヘリコプターで喜んでたのは小木先生だった
So it was Mr. Ogi who was so happy about seeing that helicopter.
But then, it must've been not long after we entered junior high.
たぶん中学に入学してすぐじゃないかな
Now that you mention it, I thought, "There are some weird teachers in this school".
言われてみれば　中学には変な教師がいるなあと
と思ったような気がする
Fuku's right, though. I don't recall seeing him ever take notice of a helicopter since then.
でも　福ちゃんの言う通り
それから小木がヘリコプターに反応したところって見たことないわね
Three years ago, huh? My memory's vague.
三年前か　記憶が曖昧だな
But now that I think about it, I don't remember Ogi doing the same thing ever again.
しかし　言われてみれば　その一回を除いて
小木が同じことをしたという覚えはない
小木先生って言えば　もっとメジャーインパクトな伝説があるけどね
There are legends about him with way more impact, though.
The Mr. Ogi Menace!
驚異の小木伝説が
Now you're just making stuff up.
勝手に作るな
No, it's the truth! Ogi told us himself.
違うよ　僕が作ったんじゃない
小木先生本人が言ってたんだ
He said... Well, I have some doubts myself,
小木先生はね　僕もちょっと信じられないんだけどね
and you probably wouldn't even believe me if I told you,
言っても信じてもらえるかどうか
but it could well be possible.
あり得ないとは思わないけどさ
Spit it out already.
速く言え
He said that in his life so far,
本人の弁によれば
he's been struck by lightning three times!
これまでの生涯で三回　雷を食らっているんだ
ええ　雷って　あの雷ですか
Lightning? You mean lightning, lightning?
Yeah. Thunder!
うん　サンダ―
Three times... It's amazing he's still in one piece.
三度も　よくご無事でしたね
It wouldn't have been much fun-der!
当たったのは三度だ
Three times... It's amazing he's still in one piece.
三度も　よくご無事でしたね
Even Chitanda's figured out how to handle Satoshi.
千反田も里志の扱いが分かってきたな
He wasn't directly hit, but he wasn't unhurt either.
直接当たったわけじゃないらしいけど
さすがに無傷ではなかったみたいだよ
He said he passed out once, and he has burn marks on his body too.
一回気を失ったこともあったらしくて
体には火傷の跡もあるんだってさ
そうですか
But he's still alive, so he's quite lucky it wasn't worse.
でもご存命なんですから　不幸中の幸いですね
That's true.
まあ　確かに
I don't remember any apparent scars though.
そういえば　目立った傷はなかったな
Struck by lightning...
雷
Three times?
それも三度も
Is that even possible?
そんなことがあるのか
Kamiyama doesn't get many lightning strikes to begin with,
神山市は　別に雷の多い土地ではない
and yet you say Ogi got hit three times alone?
それなのに小木にだけ三度も当たるものか
It doesn't seem like Satoshi would be lying.
里志が嘘を付いているわけではなさそうだ
He even said straight out that he didn't make it up.
作ったんじゃないとわざわざ前置きするくらいだからな
Truth
Lie
But then, was Ogi lying?
Truth
Lie
だとしたら　小木の嘘か
Truth
Lie
It's too obvious a lie to really be one.
嘘にしては嘘っぽ過ぎる
Wait a moment.
待ってよ
Satoshi, there were some old newspapers in the public library, right?
里志　古い新聞って図書館にあったよな
Yeah. A few.
あるよ　すこしならね
There are a few in the school's library too.
それなら図書室にもあるわよ
Though only for articles related to Kami High.
神高に関する記事だけだけどね
That won't do.
それではだめなんだ
帰る
I'm going home.
I'll drop by the library. You coming too?
図書館に寄るが　お前も来るか
Houtarou... it looks like Houtarou is actually serious about this!
奉太郎が　やる気になってるように見えるんだけど
No! I just... How should I put it...
違う
何というか
こう
Can't stop thinking about it.
気になるんだ
Houtarou! You're Houtarou, right?
奉太郎　奉太郎だよね
That Oreki Houtarou who's always saving energy, right?
あの省エネ折木奉太郎だよね
Are you being controlled by aliens?
宇宙人に乗っ取られたかな
Or were you possessed by Chitanda?
それとも千反田さんが乗り移ってるのかい
やめんか
Cut it out!
Oreki...
折木
You should go home soon.
あんた帰った方がいいわ
Go to bed early and tuck yourself in under a warm blanket.
温かくして速く寝なさい
I'm sure you'll be right as rain by tomorrow.
明日にはきっとすっきりしてるから
You're being rude!
失礼な
Is it that unusual for me to be doing something out of my own free will?
俺が自発的に行動することがそんなに異常か
まあいい　手短にやってしまおう
Whatever. Let's just get this over with already.
Oreki!
折木さん
What?
何だ
You can't stop thinking about it?
気になっているんですね
Kinda.
まあな
Are you going to investigate it?
調べに行くんですか
I might not be able to find anything.
何も出てこないかもしれないがな
I can't stop thinking about that!
気になります
Wh... What?
な　何だ
There's something in this world that can tickle even your curiosity!
折木さんの好奇心をくすぐるものがこの世に存在するなんて
I can't stop thinking about what that could be!
それって一体何なのか
私　気になります
She isn't exactly polite either.
こいつも大概失礼だな
Satoshi said he had homework and couldn't come.
里志は宿題があるため　来るとは言わなかった
Having the assistant librarian Ibara around would've been helpful,
図書委員の伊原に来てもらえると助かったのだが
but I couldn't bring myself to ask her.
頼める義理はなかった
Sorry to keep you waiting!
お待たせしました
Should we get going, then?
では　行きましょうか
You go ahead.
先に行ってくれ
二人乗りでもいいですよ
You can ride on the back.
Nope.
いや　違うだろ
Not a chance.
いや　ないな
Please just go ahead.
やっぱり先に行ってくれ
Okay then.
はい　では
Chitanda!
千反田
Yes?
はい
If there's a way to search old articles,
過去の新聞記事が検索できるようなら
look for the name Ogi Masakiyo.
小木正清という名前を調べておいてくれないか
It's written as, "a small tree, true and pure". Ogi Masakiyo.
小さい木が正しく清らかで　小木正清だ
Okay. See you later then.
分かりました
では　後で
寒露
会阴寒之气
露冷寒而欲结凝
Cold Dew
As shadows grow and the air cools,
pearl strings of dew appear.
Hyouka
According to my sister, who's been to the Kamikakiuchi mountains,
何とかあの神垣内連峰に入ったことがある姉貴が言うには
those 3000 meter high peaks cut off even the flow of the air,
3000メートル級の山々が連なる連峰は
大気の流れさえ遮ってる
so the weather on this side and the other side is totally different.
連峰のこちら側と向こう側とでは
全然気候が違うらしい
I shouldn't make Chitanda wait too long.
あまり千反田を待たせるわけにもいくまい
Kamiyama
City Library
Oreki!
折木さん
I've found something about Mr Ogi!
小木先生の情報見つかりました
"Cleaning the passes across the Kamikakiuchi mountains."
登山道美化活動神垣内連峰で
Mr. Ogi was a mountaineer.
小木先生は山登りをなさる方だったんですね
On the 26th, the Kamiyama rangers organized
26日から神山山岳会の主催で鐙岳登山道の美化が進められている
the cleaning of a path on the Abumi cliff.
Eleven people, including volunteers, took part in
ボランティアなど11名が参加し
picking up trash near the mountain path.
登山道周辺のゴミを拾った
The leader of the Kamiyama rangers, Ogi Masakiyo (39) said:
神山山岳会団長の小木正清さん（39歳）は
"Due to the mountaineering boom, there are many people who don't know the basic rules."
「登山ブームで山のマナーを知らない登山者が増えた
"I want to make it clear that when you're in the mountains, it's a matter of life and death."
山でのマナー違反は命にかかわることを知ってほしいと話した
I see. So I was right.
やはり　そっか
What do you mean?
あの　どうかしましたか
Nothing.
別に
Could you search through all the old papers?
昔の新聞は全部検索できたのか
You can see for yourself at the second floor counter.
あの　二階のカウンターで調べてもらえますよ
I'd prefer it if my predictions ended up being wrong this time...
この予想を　あまり当たってほしくないんだが
Excuse me. We'd like to search for some newspaper articles.
すみません　新聞記事を検索したいんですが
All right. What are you looking for?
はい　何を調べますか
Articles from three years ago, between March and May.
三年前の4月から5月までの記事をお願いします
Any particular keywords?
何かキーワードありますか
Look for "accident", please.
じゃ　遭難で
ええ
There are twelve results. Would you like to refine the search?
12件ありますね　絞り込みますか
That's not too many. Can we see them all?
そのくらいなら見せてください
Sure, go on.
どうぞ
Ongoing accidents among 60-70 year old people
Accident in Alaska - 5 dead
7 doctors suffer accident
Life: Ten years since the accident
Kamikakiuchi accidents, the most casualties yet: 11 wounded, 2 dead
Kamikakiuchi accident victim saved by helicopter
Man fell in the Kamikakiuchi mountains
Accident in Alaska - 5 dead
7 doctors suffer accident
Life: Ten years since the accident
Kamikakiuchi accidents, the most casualties yet: 11 wounded, 2 dead
Kamikakiuchi accident victim saved by helicopter
Man fell in the Kamikakiuchi mountains
Accident in the Kamikakiuchi mts - search in progress
7 doctors suffer accident
Life: Ten years since the accident
Kamikakiuchi accidents, the most casualties yet: 11 wounded, 2 dead
Kamikakiuchi accident victim saved by helicopter
Man fell in the Kamikakiuchi mountains
Accident in the Kamikakiuchi mts - search in progress
Guidebook to prevent accidents in the Kamikakiuchi mountains
Life: Ten years since the accident
Kamikakiuchi accidents, the most casualties yet: 11 wounded, 2 dead
Kamikakiuchi accident victim saved by helicopter
Man fell in the Kamikakiuchi mountains
Accident in the Kamikakiuchi mts - search in progress
Guidebook to prevent accidents in the Kamikakiuchi mountains
Accident in North America, 8 dead, 2 unconscious
Kamikakiuchi accidents, the most casualties yet: 11 wounded, 2 dead
Kamikakiuchi accident victim saved by helicopter
Man fell in the Kamikakiuchi mountains
Accident in the Kamikakiuchi mts - search in progress
Guidebook to prevent accidents in the Kamikakiuchi mountains
Accident in North America, 8 dead, 2 unconscious
Mountain accident: 8 missing, also 4 veteran mountaineers
Kamikakiuchi accident victim saved by helicopter
Man fell in the Kamikakiuchi mountains
Accident in the Kamikakiuchi mts - search in progress
Guidebook to prevent accidents in the Kamikakiuchi mountains
Accident in North America, 8 dead, 2 unconscious
Mountain accident: 8 missing, also 4 veteran mountaineers
Found it.
見つけた
Accident in the Kamikakiuchi mts - search in progress
It's from May 9th, right?
5月9日の記事ですね
Excuse me, could we read these articles?
あの　すみません　この新聞記事は見られますか
Chitanda's on to it too.
千反田も事情察したな
Maruto, could you help for a moment?
丸田さん　ちょっとお願いします
What's it?
どうしたの
We'd like to see newspaper articles from May 9th, three years ago.
あの　三年前の5月9日の新聞記事が見たいんですけど
Three years ago?
三年前ね　ちょっと待ってて
Sure, be right back.
はい　ありがとうございます
Thank you very much.
Ah, it'll probably take about half an hour to get the articles. Is that okay?
ああ　記事を出してくるのに30分ぐらい掛かるけど　いい
Sure.
分かりました
I'll let you know when it's done.
準備ができたら呼びますから
Thank you.
よろしくお願いします
Oreki, now that we're here, want to have a look around?
折木さん　せっかくですし　少し見て回りませんか
I guess we could.
そうだな
Ah, it's a Taira-no-Kiyomori special this time.
今回は平清盛特集ですね
The cover's so pretty!
表紙がきれい
In this special he's portrayed as the son of the Shirakawa emperor.
この特集では平清盛は白河院の子供として描かれているのか
There are people who believe that he is.
確かにそういう説もありますけど
Whoa, nice one.
ほー　大したもんだ
It's the Itsukushima shrine at Miyajima. I'd like to go there one day.
宮島　厳島神社ですね
ぜひ一度行ってみたいです
Vegetables Made Exciting
Look at all the cabbages!
キャベツがいっぱいです　色がきれいですね
They're such a nice color!
あっ　今度はトマトがいっぱいです
And there's so many tomatoes!
They all look so delicious!
どれもおいしそうです
That reminds me, Oreki! Our shiitake harvest was quite good this year.
そういえば　折木さん
家でとれた椎茸がいっぱいあるんですけど
Would you like some?
よかったらどうです
あっ　昆虫の本ですよ　折木さん
Look! Books about bugs, Oreki!
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Dung Beetles
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Dung Beetles
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Dung Beetles
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Dung Beetles
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Dung Beetles
Honeybee Journal
A Bee's Life
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Dung Beetles
Honeybee Journal
Yamamoto Chiyoko
Dung Beetles
This one's about dung beetles.
ふんころがしですね
Dung Beetles
They're so cute!
可愛いです
Why did you pick that one?
なぜそっちを選ぶ
Is there anything you'd like to see, Oreki?
折木さんは何か見たいものありますか
Famous Castles of
Japan
Well...
そうだな
Wow, isn't that castle huge? It's majestic.
広くて立派なお城ですね
Your home's quite big too.
お前の家も十分に広いだろう
Not quite this big.
家の家はそんなに広くないですよ
Maybe just a little bigger than average.
普通よりは少し広いぐらいでしょうか
What exactly do you define as average?
お前の言う普通の基準が分からん
で　どうでしたか
Any luck?
They're in this file. Please take a look through it.
こちらのフャイルにまとめられているから
この中から探して
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
Whoa, it's heavy.
おっ　重い
There's quite a few.
かなりあるな
あっ　5月9日の新聞です
This is the newspaper from May 9th!
This is probably the day on which Ogi said he loved helicopters.
小木が授業中にヘリコプターが好きだと表明したのは
たぶんこの日だ
Two Kamiyama rangers in accident
There.
あった
Two Kamiyama rangers in accident
So... what does this mean?
つまり　どういうことなんでしょう
It means that Ogi had no particular love for helicopters.
つまり小木はヘリコプターなんか好きじゃなかったんだ
It's probably true that Ogi's been struck by lightning three times,
小木には三度も雷が落ちた
たぶん本当の話だろう
but can you imagine that happening to an English teacher in this town?
だが普通にこの町で英語教師をして　るだけで
そんなに雷が落ちるか
That's true.
確かにそうですね
So I thought,
それでふと思ったんだ
what if he often goes somewhere with lots of lightning strikes?
小木は雷が落ちやすい場所によく行くんじゃないかって
Up in the mountains, right?
それが山だったんですね
Is that what you guessed?
折木さんは予想していたんですか
Kind of.
なんとなくな
I thought, what if he wasn't just a teacher, but a mountaineer as well?
小木は教師であると同時に　登山家だったんじゃないかと思ったんだ
I came here to make sure.
だから　まさかと思ってここに確認に来た
Why would Ogi have paid special attention to that helicopter on that day?
どうしてあの日だけ小木はヘリを見ようとしたのか
Because it must've had some special significance.
そのヘリに特別な意味があったからだ
Ogi was waiting for a helicopter to fly by.
小木はその日ヘリが飛ぶことを心待ちにしていたんだ
Which means?
と　言いますと
He must've been very nervous as to whether or not the helicopter would fly out.
もう少し言うと　小木はその日
ヘリが飛ぶかどうかどうしても気がかりだった
That's why he rushed to the window the moment he heard the noise.
だから音を聞いて　思わず機体を確認したんだ
An English teacher being worried about a helicopter doesn't mean much.
英語教師がヘリを気にしたと言うだけでは　何も分からない
But if he was a mountaineer as well, that's a whole different story.
ところが　登山家がヘリを気にしていたのであれば　話は別だ
Kamiyama is bordered by the Kamikakiuchi mountains,
ここ神山市は　3000メートル級の山々が連なる
神垣内連峰が控える町
A mountaineer from the city was worried about a helicopter.
この町の登山家がヘリを気にしていた
It could've been for aerial photography, transporting supplies, or...
空撮か資材運搬か
でなければ
Or?
An emergency.
救難だ
...sudden change in weather for the worse...
An emergency...
救難
This article says that on the 8th, the weather was so bad that helicopters couldn't fly.
この記事には　8日は天気が悪くて
ヘリコプターが飛べなかったと書いてあります
Yeah...
そうだな
Ogi was worried about whether the prefectural police helicopter would fly over us.
小木は県警のヘリが飛べるか気にしていた
Even during class, he had the weather conditions in the Kamikakiuchi mountains on his mind.
授業をしながらも　神垣内連峰の天候回復を気にしていた
If helicopters were able to fly, that meant the weather had improved.
連峰が晴れていればヘリは飛ぶ
And if the weather had improved, the victims of the accident had a much greater chance of survival.
晴れていれば遭難者の生存率も変わってくる
I wonder how he must have felt at the time.
小木先生はどんなお気持ちだったんでしょう
I don't know how he felt, but I think I saw him smile.
気持ちは分からんが
たぶん笑っていたと思う
We had a look through the papers from the next few days too.
新聞を何日か先の文まで目を通した
The bodies of the two victims of the accident were found.
遭難した二人は遺体で発見されていた
And it was the prefectural police helicopter that found them.
見つけたのは県警のヘリだった
Um...
あの
Hm?
うん
Can I ask you a question?
一つ　聞いてもいいですか
Go on.
どうぞ
Why did you get so interested in this?
どうして気になったんですか
Is it so strange for me to want to look something up myself?
俺が自発的に調べるのはそんなに奇妙か
Well, yeah. I was thinking it wasn't like you at all.
ええ　そうですね
折木さんらしくないような気がしました
I guess. After all, I don't usually do anything I don't have to.
まあ　確かに　いつもはやらなくてもいいことならやらないからな
いいえ　そういうことではなくてですね
Oh, that's not what I meant.
Damn, she just straight-out ignored my cool motto.
俺の不変のモットーがあっさりと退けられた
You can work hard for other people's sakes.
折木さんはほかの人のためにはいろいろ力を尽します
You've helped me a bunch of times as well.
私も何度も助けてもらいました
This is a terrible misunderstanding you have here.
とんでもない誤解だ
But you don't really care about yourself, right?
でも折木さんって自分のことには無頓着ですよね
Then why did you bother confirming your own hunch today?
それなのに　どうして今日だけは自分の疑問を調べたんですか
Sorry,
すみません
うん
but I can't stop thinking about it!
私　どうしても気になるんです
When I heard the lightning story from Satoshi, I had a bad feeling.
里志から雷のことを聞いて
嫌な連想が浮かんだんだ
Yes, you said that.
はい　そう言ってましたね
So, I wanted to check if my intuition was correct.
その連想が当たっているかはっきりさせたかった
That's why I went to the library to investigate.
だから調べに行こうと思った
それで　図書館さ
It would've been different if it'd needed a week-long investigation or something,
一週間も籠ってやるような大調査だったら別だが
but looking through old newspapers isn't a big deal.
古い新聞をめくるだけのことなら大したことはない
I even had help.
手伝いもいたし
If my hunch was right, we'd need to be careful.
連想が当たっていたら　気をつけなきゃいけないことだからな
Careful?
気をつける　ですか
If something like that had happened, Ogi couldn't just say he loved helicopters that easily.
実際はああいうことがあったのに
小木はヘリが好きだったななんて気楽には言えない
Unless he was really that insensitive. It's best to be careful with people like that.
それは無神経ってことだ
それはさすがに気をつけるさ
うん　分かりにくかったか
Was it that difficult to understand?
Insensitive as in,
無神経というか　あれだ
he has no idea how other people are feeling.
人の気も知らないでっていう感じだ
Though I'll probably never meet him again,
たぶん二度と小木には会わないから
so it's not much of a concern.
人の気も何もないけどな
Oreki!
折木さん
それって　とっても
That's... so...
I can't put in words...
うまく言えません
What's she trying to say?
こいつは何を言おうとしたんだ
If she can't put it in words, she wouldn't be able to tell me even if I asked.
まいいか
うまく言えないことなら　うまく聞き出せないだろうし
All right, let's call it a day.
じゃあ　ここで
Thanks for your help.
今日は手伝ってくれて助かった
You're welcome.
どういたしまして
I'm glad I could see an unexpected side of you.
今日は折木さんの意外な一面が見られてよかったです
Give me a break.
もう　勘弁してくれ
おっ　すみません
Sorry...
See you tomorrow!
では　また
It'll be totally dark by the time she gets home.
千反田が家に着く頃は完全に夜だな
She came along of her own free will. I didn't ask her to.
ついてくると言ったのは千反田のほうだ
俺が頼んだわけじゃない
But still...
でも
I guess I owe her one.
やっぱり借りかな
これは
状況は非科学的に 感情のモンタージュ
The situation is unscientific
A montage of emotions
誰が誰を呼んでる
Who's calling who?
You look away when our eyes are about to meet
振り向けば逃げてく視線（感じる）
I can feel it
気のせいじゃつれないよ アンテナは才能って言うでしょ
Am I just imagining things? It's so cold of you
It takes talent to read minds
だって（だって） 知りたい（君は違うの？）
You know
I wanna know
Don't you?
I'll fix the fire of youth in your heart while I can
青春の温度差 今のうち正してあげるよ
If we can do it today why leave it for tomorrow
明日解決するなら 今でもよくない？
君のミステリー解いてみたい
I want to solve your mystery
少年の秘密めいた背中探せ（今日も）
Look for the back of the boy, burdened with secrets
Even today
You are a fantasy and I'm drawn to you
君はファンタジー 惹かれてゆくよ（ずるい）
This growing curiosity
膨らんだ好奇心 とりたくはないのに
There's no twist in the story
気になるよ 興味深い どうして
I can't stop thinking about it
It's so interesting
But why?
次回　心あたりのある者は
Next time: Those Whom It May Concern.
Those Whom It May Concern